<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sexual reward | Conall Mac Cionnaith</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/sexual-reward/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/sexual-reward/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>sexual reward</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/img/themes/academic/assets/images/icon.png</url>
      <title>sexual reward</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/sexual-reward/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behavior is the ultimate arbiter: An alternative explanation for the inhibitory effect of fluoxetine on the ovulatory homolog model of orgasm in rabbits</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publication/quintan-mac-cionnaith-pfaus-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publication/quintan-mac-cionnaith-pfaus-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo Academic&amp;rsquo;s Markdown slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code and math&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The facilitating effects of acute oxytocin treatment on pacing and proceptive sexual behaviours are dose-dependent</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posters/sfn2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posters/sfn2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conall E. Mac Cionnaith, Eamonn L. Gomez-Perales, Wayne G. Brake and James G. Pfaus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presented at Society for Neuroscience 2019 Chicago&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accepted abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several studies have reported that oxytocin (OT) administration increases lordosis quotients in female rats. However, the lordosis reflex is only one of many behaviours that are important during mating in the female rat. Proceptive behaviours (i.e. solicitations and hops and darts) and pacing are important for successful impregnation. Therefore, the current study tests the effects of different doses of oxytocin on a variety of sexual behavioural measures. Thirty female Long-Evans (LE) rats were randomised to be intraperitoneally injected with 20µg OT, 50µg OT, or saline one minute prior to copulation (n = 10 per group). Females copulated with an LE male in unilevel Plexiglass pacing chambers for 30 minutes. Trials were recorded and scored for: female entries to the male compartment, the latency to return to the male after leaving the male’s compartment, solicitations, hops and darts, intromissions and ejaculations received, and the amount of time spent with a male. All behaviours were analysed with one-way ANOVAs, followed by Holm-adjusted group comparisons. Females treated with 50µg OT took longer to return to the male chamber and made fewer entries to the male’s compartment compared to the 20µg OT group. They also received fewer intromissions and ejaculations. Additionally, females treated with 50µg OT made fewer hops and darts and fewer solicitations than females given 20µg OT. Conversely, 20µg OT females made more proceptive behaviours and entries to the male compartment compared to 50µg OT females. There was also a trend for females given 20µg OT to make more solicitations and hops and darts than saline treated females. Thus, OT may acutely facilitate female sexual behaviour, but these effects are dose dependent; 20µg OT facilitates sexual behaviours whereas 50µg OT is inhibitory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Differential disruption of conditioned ejaculatory preference in the male rat based on different sensory modalities by micro-infusions of naloxone to the medial preoptic area or ventral tegmental area</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publication/quintana-et-al.-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publication/quintana-et-al.-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo Academic&amp;rsquo;s Markdown slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code and math&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The facilitating effect of oxytocin on sexually conditioned partner preference in the female rat</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posters/bna2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posters/bna2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conall E. Mac Cionnaith, Eamonn Gomez-Perales, Rebecca Cernik, Marjolaine Rivest-Beauregard, Alice Lemay,
Lisa Thomasse, Wayne Brake &amp;amp; James G. Pfaus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presented at the British Neuroscience Assocation Festival of Neuroscience in Dublin 2019&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accepted preregistered abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A growing body of evidence shows important roles of Pavlovian learning in sexual partner selection. Female rats who repeatedly copulate with almond scented males selectively solicit, and preferentially receive the scented male’s ejaculations, relative to an unscented male. In female prairie voles, partner preference formation is blocked by the administration of an oxytocin receptor antagonist and is facilitated by oxytocin. Previous studies examining sexually conditioned partner preference in the female rat have typically required ten conditioning trials prior to partner preference emerging. The aim of this study is to examine whether oxytocin facilitates faster formation of sexually conditioned partner preference in female rats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: Hormonally-primed ovariectomised Long-Evans female rats (N=72) will be given either one, five, or ten sexual conditioning trials with an almond scented male prior to an open-field partner preference test. Females will be injected intraperitoneally with either 20µg of oxytocin or saline one minute before conditioning trials (n=12). In the partner preference test, an almond scented and an unscented male will be tethered to opposite corners of the open field, allowing the female to copulate preferentially with either male. Partner preference tests will be recorded and then scored by a blinded observer for 1) solicitations made toward the scented and unscented males, 2) ejaculations received by the female from each male, and 3) the female’s choice for first solicitation and ejaculation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approach for statistical analysis: Each behaviour will be analysed with a 3x2x2 three-way mixed ANOVA. We hypothesise a three-way interaction between drug treatment, number of conditioning trials, and the type of male (scented vs unscented). Specifically, females given one and five conditioning trials with oxytocin will solicit and receive more ejaculations from the scented male compared to the unscented male, and this effect will not be present in the saline treated groups. At ten trials we expect no differences in solicitations made toward and ejaculations received from the scented male between the oxytocin and saline treated females. The choice for first ejaculation and solicitation will be analysed using  χ2 tests. Sample size was calculated to achieve 90% power with a medium effect size.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fos expression in female rats with a conditioned partner preference for an individual male</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posters/sfn2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posters/sfn2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conall E. Mac Cionnaith, Alice Lemay, Eamonn Gomez-Perales, Genevieve Robert, Rebecca Cernik and James G. Pfaus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presented at Society for Neuroscience 2018 San Diego&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accepted abstract&lt;/strong&gt;
A growing body of evidence shows important roles of Pavlovian learning in sexual partner selection. Female rats who repeatedly undergo paced copulation with almond scented males selectively solicit, and preferentially receive the scented male’s ejaculations relative to those of an unscented male. Exposure to conditioned scented partner cues has been shown to induce Fos protein within oxytocin (OT) neurons in the paraventricular nucleus (PVN) of the hypothalamus. Whether female rats can be conditioned to show a partner preference for an individual male rat has not yet been shown. The aim of this study was to test whether female rats could form a conditioned preference for an individual male rat. Females were given paced copulation with either a one-hole divider or a fourhole divider in a unilevel pacing chamber but always copulated with the same partner during conditioning trials (N = 32). After 10 trials, females were then given an open-field partner preference test with the partner male and a novel male. Females underwent two reconditioning trials and were then exposed to the partner or a novel male for an hour to induce Fos protein, after which we examined regions of the brain associated with incentive motivation, sexual behaviour, and bonding (nucleus accumbens core and shell, medial preoptic area, and ventral tegmental area). Fos protein was also examined in OT-labelled neurons within the PVN and supraoptic nucleus (SON). Behavioural results indicated that females in the one-hole pacing group received the first ejaculation more frequently and more ejaculations overall from the partner male compared to the novel male. The four-hole pacing group did not display a conditioned partner preference. Preliminary counts in the PVN (n = 3) did not show a significant difference in Fos/OT co-labelled cells, but, there is a trend toward an interaction between the male females were exposed to and the pacing group (p &amp;lt; .10, η²p =.141). Preliminary result suggest this interaction is being driven by increased activation in females in the one-hole group exposed to the partner male. The behavioural data suggest that pacing is necessary but not sufficient for the formation of conditioned partner preference for an individual male rat. We expect that exposure to the partner in the one-hole pacing will show differential Fos expression compared to females exposed to a novel male and will not be present in the four-hole group. If this effect is found it would suggest that activation of OT cells in the PVN are likely involved in the display of conditioned partner preference for individual male rats as well as for conditioned odour cues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The orgasm gap and what sex-ed did not teach you</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/orgasm_gap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/orgasm_gap/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reposted from 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/the-orgasm-gap-and-what-sex-ed-did-not-teach-you-92237&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;theconversation.ca&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a clear disparity between men and women when it comes to achieving orgasm; a phenomenon scientists call the orgasm gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studying orgasms is no easy task. We work as psychology of sexual behaviour researchers in the lab of Dr. James Pfaus at Concordia University and were interested to explore the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27791968&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;“controversy”&lt;/a&gt; of clitoral versus vaginal orgasms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We conducted a literature review on the current state of the evidence and different perspectives on how this phenomenon occurs in women. Particularly, the nature of a woman’s orgasm has been a source of scientific, political and cultural debate for over a century. Although 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0272735800000696?via%3Dihub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;science has an idea&lt;/a&gt; of what orgasms are, we are still quite uncertain as to how they occur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://psycnet.apa.org/record/1966-35042-000&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Orgasms&lt;/a&gt; are one of the few phenomena that occur as a result of a highly complex interaction of several physiological and psychological systems all at once. While there may be evolutionary reasons why 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5087694/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;men&lt;/a&gt; are more likely to orgasm during sex, we shouldn’t doom ourselves to this idea. Indeed, part of the problem lies in what happens in the bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all have different preferences when it comes to what we like in bed. But one commonality we share is that we know when we orgasm and when we do not. We don’t always orgasm every time we have sex, and that can be just fine, because we may have sex for many different reasons. However, studies repeatedly show that women reach climax less often than men do during sexual encounters together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, a national survey conducted in the United States showed that 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.ca/books/about/The_Social_Organization_of_Sexuality.html?id=72AHO0rE2HoC&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;women reported one orgasm for every three from men&lt;/a&gt;. Heterosexual males said they achieved orgasm usually or always during sexual intimacy, 95 per cent of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gap appears to become narrower among homosexual and bisexual people, where 89 per cent of gay males, 88 per cent bisexual males, 86 per cent lesbian women, and 66 per cent of bisexual women orgasm during sexual interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we take a closer look at what might explain the orgasm gap, we can see the type of relationship we have with our partner matters. If you are in an established committed relationship, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0003122412445802&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the gap tends to close&lt;/a&gt;, but it widens during casual sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0003122412445802&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;women in a committed relationship&lt;/a&gt; report reaching an orgasm as often as 86 per cent of the time, whereas women in casual sex encounters report they orgasm only 39 per cent of the time. Furthermore, heterosexual women achieve orgasm easily and regularly through masturbation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, the more knowledge about the female genitalia (especially about the clitoris) the partner has, the higher the likelihood is for women to orgasm more frequently. Finally, and most importantly, the respondents reported the most reliable practice to achieve an orgasm for women is oral sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t know why this gap occurs in casual sex versus sex in a committed relationship, but part of it might be how we communicate what we want sexually, what we expect sexually and attitudes toward sexual pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What sex-ed did not teach you&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formal education teaches us a vast amount of relevant topics in school, yet sexual education has been and is still a matter of (moral) debate. For many of us, sexual education covered reproductive biology and how not to get pregnant or contract sexually transmitted infections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sex-ed has 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC198355/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;been focused&lt;/a&gt; on preventing kids from having sex. “Always use condoms” was sometimes the most progressive sex-ed message. Education is now progressing into teaching what sex is about and how to engage in ethical and respectful sex, but that is still not the whole picture. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/fun-sex-is-healthy-sex-why-isnt-that-on-the-curriculum-81020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;How about pleasure or how to have fun&lt;/a&gt; and to explore what we like, how to communicate to our partners and many other crucial aspects of intimate life?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key to the ultimate goal of enjoying ourselves is to know what you and your partner want and how to satisfy each other. Consequently, incomplete and biased sex education fails both men and women, omitting the fact sex is not only for reproduction but also for enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the first thing we should learn about sex is that it is one of the favourite pastimes of adults. Preventing it from happening will only increase the likelihood of future generations engaging in it more, only with less knowledge about to how get the most out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some advice for sexual partners&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first reaction to the orgasm gap may be to point fingers and find someone to blame: Cultural attitudes, religion, society, the educational system, your ex. Certainly, anyone would agree that the gap is a multifactorial phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statistics do not count when it comes to your own intimacy. In bed, it’s you and your partner(s), and that is what matters. We cannot create nor do we trigger orgasms in our partners. We can only help to make them easier, more fun and more enjoyable for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you may have a good idea of what your partner may want in bed, what people like varies a great deal. Thus, understanding what a partner wants, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/peggy_orenstein_what_young_women_believe_about_their_own_sexual_pleasure&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;how, when, where, or for how long, requires openness, trust and, most importantly, communication&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These key ingredients may be what’s missing in both casual and long-term encounters. We could all be more open and humble, and acknowledge that with a good attitude and a good teacher, everyone gets better at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your sexual prowess and ability to satisfy grows with practice; it goes without saying that our sexual lives should improve beyond previous negative experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There may be very few things in this world that perhaps all people in this world enjoy, and orgasms are among them. But the enjoyment of sex is not the race to climb to the top of the mountain. Instead, it is the enjoyment of getting there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what can you do? Talk, be confident and pay attention to your partner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Satisfaction means very different things for different people. What really matters is what you and your partner(s) want. Shattering the climax glass ceiling is a team effort. Sex is fun — and everyone has something to learn about it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The whole versus the sum of some of the parts: toward resolving the apparent controversy of clitoral versus vaginal orgasms</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publication/pfaus-et-al.-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publication/pfaus-et-al.-2016/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo Academic&amp;rsquo;s Markdown slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code and math&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
