<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>female sexual behaviour | Conall Mac Cionnaith</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/female-sexual-behaviour/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/female-sexual-behaviour/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>female sexual behaviour</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>©</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/img/themes/academic/assets/images/icon.png</url>
      <title>female sexual behaviour</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/female-sexual-behaviour/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The non-aromatizable androgen dihydrotestosterone (DHT) facilitates sexual behavior in ovariectomized female rats primed with estradiol</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publication/maseroli-et-al.-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publication/maseroli-et-al.-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Cite&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo the feature to enable visitors to import publication metadata into their reference management software.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo Academic&amp;rsquo;s Markdown slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplementary notes can be added here, including 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;code and math&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The facilitating effects of acute oxytocin treatment on pacing and proceptive sexual behaviours are dose-dependent</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posters/sfn2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posters/sfn2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conall E. Mac Cionnaith, Eamonn L. Gomez-Perales, Wayne G. Brake and James G. Pfaus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presented at Society for Neuroscience 2019 Chicago&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accepted abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several studies have reported that oxytocin (OT) administration increases lordosis quotients in female rats. However, the lordosis reflex is only one of many behaviours that are important during mating in the female rat. Proceptive behaviours (i.e. solicitations and hops and darts) and pacing are important for successful impregnation. Therefore, the current study tests the effects of different doses of oxytocin on a variety of sexual behavioural measures. Thirty female Long-Evans (LE) rats were randomised to be intraperitoneally injected with 20µg OT, 50µg OT, or saline one minute prior to copulation (n = 10 per group). Females copulated with an LE male in unilevel Plexiglass pacing chambers for 30 minutes. Trials were recorded and scored for: female entries to the male compartment, the latency to return to the male after leaving the male’s compartment, solicitations, hops and darts, intromissions and ejaculations received, and the amount of time spent with a male. All behaviours were analysed with one-way ANOVAs, followed by Holm-adjusted group comparisons. Females treated with 50µg OT took longer to return to the male chamber and made fewer entries to the male’s compartment compared to the 20µg OT group. They also received fewer intromissions and ejaculations. Additionally, females treated with 50µg OT made fewer hops and darts and fewer solicitations than females given 20µg OT. Conversely, 20µg OT females made more proceptive behaviours and entries to the male compartment compared to 50µg OT females. There was also a trend for females given 20µg OT to make more solicitations and hops and darts than saline treated females. Thus, OT may acutely facilitate female sexual behaviour, but these effects are dose dependent; 20µg OT facilitates sexual behaviours whereas 50µg OT is inhibitory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The facilitating effect of oxytocin on sexually conditioned partner preference in the female rat</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posters/bna2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posters/bna2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conall E. Mac Cionnaith, Eamonn Gomez-Perales, Rebecca Cernik, Marjolaine Rivest-Beauregard, Alice Lemay,
Lisa Thomasse, Wayne Brake &amp;amp; James G. Pfaus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presented at the British Neuroscience Assocation Festival of Neuroscience in Dublin 2019&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accepted preregistered abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A growing body of evidence shows important roles of Pavlovian learning in sexual partner selection. Female rats who repeatedly copulate with almond scented males selectively solicit, and preferentially receive the scented male’s ejaculations, relative to an unscented male. In female prairie voles, partner preference formation is blocked by the administration of an oxytocin receptor antagonist and is facilitated by oxytocin. Previous studies examining sexually conditioned partner preference in the female rat have typically required ten conditioning trials prior to partner preference emerging. The aim of this study is to examine whether oxytocin facilitates faster formation of sexually conditioned partner preference in female rats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods: Hormonally-primed ovariectomised Long-Evans female rats (N=72) will be given either one, five, or ten sexual conditioning trials with an almond scented male prior to an open-field partner preference test. Females will be injected intraperitoneally with either 20µg of oxytocin or saline one minute before conditioning trials (n=12). In the partner preference test, an almond scented and an unscented male will be tethered to opposite corners of the open field, allowing the female to copulate preferentially with either male. Partner preference tests will be recorded and then scored by a blinded observer for 1) solicitations made toward the scented and unscented males, 2) ejaculations received by the female from each male, and 3) the female’s choice for first solicitation and ejaculation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Approach for statistical analysis: Each behaviour will be analysed with a 3x2x2 three-way mixed ANOVA. We hypothesise a three-way interaction between drug treatment, number of conditioning trials, and the type of male (scented vs unscented). Specifically, females given one and five conditioning trials with oxytocin will solicit and receive more ejaculations from the scented male compared to the unscented male, and this effect will not be present in the saline treated groups. At ten trials we expect no differences in solicitations made toward and ejaculations received from the scented male between the oxytocin and saline treated females. The choice for first ejaculation and solicitation will be analysed using  χ2 tests. Sample size was calculated to achieve 90% power with a medium effect size.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fos expression in female rats with a conditioned partner preference for an individual male</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posters/sfn2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posters/sfn2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conall E. Mac Cionnaith, Alice Lemay, Eamonn Gomez-Perales, Genevieve Robert, Rebecca Cernik and James G. Pfaus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presented at Society for Neuroscience 2018 San Diego&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accepted abstract&lt;/strong&gt;
A growing body of evidence shows important roles of Pavlovian learning in sexual partner selection. Female rats who repeatedly undergo paced copulation with almond scented males selectively solicit, and preferentially receive the scented male’s ejaculations relative to those of an unscented male. Exposure to conditioned scented partner cues has been shown to induce Fos protein within oxytocin (OT) neurons in the paraventricular nucleus (PVN) of the hypothalamus. Whether female rats can be conditioned to show a partner preference for an individual male rat has not yet been shown. The aim of this study was to test whether female rats could form a conditioned preference for an individual male rat. Females were given paced copulation with either a one-hole divider or a fourhole divider in a unilevel pacing chamber but always copulated with the same partner during conditioning trials (N = 32). After 10 trials, females were then given an open-field partner preference test with the partner male and a novel male. Females underwent two reconditioning trials and were then exposed to the partner or a novel male for an hour to induce Fos protein, after which we examined regions of the brain associated with incentive motivation, sexual behaviour, and bonding (nucleus accumbens core and shell, medial preoptic area, and ventral tegmental area). Fos protein was also examined in OT-labelled neurons within the PVN and supraoptic nucleus (SON). Behavioural results indicated that females in the one-hole pacing group received the first ejaculation more frequently and more ejaculations overall from the partner male compared to the novel male. The four-hole pacing group did not display a conditioned partner preference. Preliminary counts in the PVN (n = 3) did not show a significant difference in Fos/OT co-labelled cells, but, there is a trend toward an interaction between the male females were exposed to and the pacing group (p &amp;lt; .10, η²p =.141). Preliminary result suggest this interaction is being driven by increased activation in females in the one-hole group exposed to the partner male. The behavioural data suggest that pacing is necessary but not sufficient for the formation of conditioned partner preference for an individual male rat. We expect that exposure to the partner in the one-hole pacing will show differential Fos expression compared to females exposed to a novel male and will not be present in the four-hole group. If this effect is found it would suggest that activation of OT cells in the PVN are likely involved in the display of conditioned partner preference for individual male rats as well as for conditioned odour cues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
